Sydney. I had been waiting my whole life to get to Sydney.
سيدني. لطالما تمنيت زيارة سيدني.
I got to the airport, to the hotel, checked in,
وصلت إلى المطار، ثم الفندق وحجزت غرفتي
and, sitting there in the lobby, was a brochure
وأثناء جلوسي في الردهة
for the Sydney Festival. I thumbed through it,
لمحت نشرة عن "مهرجان سيدني"
and I came across a show called "Minto: Live."
تفقدتها، ولاحظت عرضا بعنوان "مينتو: لايف"
The description read: "The suburban streets of Minto
وصفه كالتالي: "شوارع ضاحية مينتو
become the stage for performances
تتحول إلى منصة مسرح
created by international artists
لعروض ألفها فنانون عالميون
in collaboration with the people of Minto."
بالتعاون مع سكان مينتو."
What was this place called Minto?
ما هي ضاحية مينتو؟
Sydney, as I would learn, is a city of suburbs,
سيدني، كما علمت، مدينة ضواحي
and Minto lies southwest, about an hour away.
وتقع مينتو في المنطقة الجنوبية الغربية، وتبعد ساعة تقريبا
I have to say, it wasn't exactly what I had in mind
أعترف أنها لم تكن كما تخيلت
for my first day down under.
بعد يومي الأول في الجنوب
I mean, I'd thought about the Harbour Bridge or Bondi Beach,
كنت أتوقع رؤية "هاربر بريدج" أو "بوندي بيتش"
but Minto? But still, I'm a producer,
وليس مينتو، لكني منتج
and the lure of a site-specific theater project
وإغراء مشاهدة موقع مسرحي جديد
was more than I could resist. (Laughter)
لا يمكنني مقاومته(ضحك)
So, off I went into Friday afternoon traffic,
لذا، ذهبت بعد ظهر الجمعة
and I'll never forget what I saw when I got there.
ولن أنس ما رأيته هناك
For the performance, the audience walked
العرض كالتالي، يتنقل الجمهور
around the neighborhood from house to house,
داخل الضاحية من بيت إلى بيت
and the residents, who were the performers,
والسكان، وهم أبطال العرض،
they came out of their houses, and they performed
يخرجون من بيوتهم،
these autobiographical dances on their lawns,
ليرقصوا في الساحات أمام منازلهم
on their driveways. (Laughter)
وفي الممرات. (ضحك)
The show is a collaboration with a U.K.-based
العرض يتم بالتعاون مع شركة
performance company called Lone Twin.
مقرها في بريطانيا، اسمها "لون توين"
Lone Twin had come to Minto and worked
أتت "لون توين" إلى مينتو
with the residents, and they had created these dances.
ودربت السكان، وأخرجوا هذه الرقصات
This Australian-Indian girl, she came out and started
خرجت هذه الفتاة الأسترالية الهندية
to dance on her front lawn,
وبدأت في الرقص أمام منزلها
and her father peered out the window to see
فنظر أبوها من النافذة
what all the noise and commotion was about,
ليعرف سبب الضجة بالخارج
and he soon joined her.
وبعد قليل التحق بها
And he was followed by her little sister.
ثم جاءت أختها الصغيرة
And soon they were all dancing this joyous,
وبدأ الكل يرقص هذه الرقصات المرحة
exuberant dance right there on their lawn. (Laughter)
على العشب أمام المنزل (ضحك)
And as I walked through the neighborhood,
وأثناء تجولي في الحي
I was amazed and I was moved by the incredible
أدهشني كثيرا ما رأيت
sense of ownership this community clearly felt
من إحساس السكان
about this event.
بأنهم أصحاب هذا الحدث
"Minto: Live" brought Sydneysiders into dialogue
"مينتو: لايف" سمح بتفاعل سكان المناطق المغمورة في سيدني
with international artists, and really celebrated
مع فنانين عالميين،
the diversity of Sydney on its own terms.
كما احتفي بتنوع السكان على طريقته الخاصة
The Sydney Festival which produced "Minto: Live" I think
مهرجان سيدني الذي أنتج "مينتو: لايف"
represents a new kind of 21st-century arts festival.
يقدم نوعا جديدا من مهرجانات فن القرن 21
These festivals are radically open.
هذه المهرجانات علنية ومفتوحة
They can transform cities and communities.
ويمكنها أن تغير مدنا ومجتمعات
To understand this, I think it kind of makes sense
لنفهم هذا،
to look where we've come from.
علينا العودة إلى المكان الذي نشأت به
Modern arts festivals were born
ولدت مهرجانات الفنون الحديثة
in the rubble of World War II.
في أنقاض الحرب العالمية الثانية
Civic leaders created these annual events
كان القادة يقيمون مثل هذه الأحداث السنوية
to celebrate culture as the highest
للاحتفال بالثقافة كأسمى وسائل التعبير
expression of the human spirit.
للنفس البشرية
In 1947, the Edinburgh Festival was born
في 1947، ولد مهرجان إيدنبرج
and Avignon was born and hundreds of others
وتلاه مهرجان أفيجنون
would follow in their wake.
ومئات المهرجانات الأخرى
The work they did was very, very high art,
والتي قدمت فنا رفيع المستوى
and stars came along like Laurie Anderson
وأخرجت نجوما مثل (لوري أندرسون)
and Merce Cunningham and Robert Lepage
و (ميرس كانينجهام) و (روبرت ليباج)
who made work for this circuit,
الذين ظهروا من دائرة المهرجانات
and you had these seminal shows like "The Mahabharata"
وأيضا العروض البارزة مثل "ماهاباراتا"
and the monumental "Einstein on the Beach."
والعرض الضخم "أينشتين على الشاطيء"
But as the decades passed,
لكن بمرور الزمن
these festivals, they really became the establishment,
أصبحت هذه المهرجانات أساسية
and as the culture and capital accelerated,
وبتسارع الثقافة والرأسمالية
the Internet brought us all together,
وتقريب الإنترنت فيما بيننا
high and low kind of disappeared,
واختفاء الفروق بيننا نوعا ما
a new kind of festival emerged.
ظهر نوع آخر من المهرجانات
The old festivals, they continued to thrive, but
المهرجانات القديمة واصلت ازدهارها،
from Brighton to Rio to Perth, something new was emerging,
لكن من "برنجتون" إلى "ريو" وحتى "بيرث"،ظهرت مهرجانات جديدة
and these festivals were really different.
والتي كانت مختلفة تماما
They're open, these festivals, because, like in Minto,
يميزها أنها مفتوحة، كما في "مينتو"
they understand that the dialogue
لأنها تفهم أن الحوار
between the local and the global is essential.
بين المحلي والعالمي ضروري
They're open because they ask the audience to be a player,
مفتوحة لأنها تطلب من الجمهور التفاعل معها
a protagonist, a partner, rather than a passive spectator,
وقيادتها والمشاركة بها،لا أن يكون مجرد مشاهد سلبي
and they're open because they know that imagination
مفتوحة لأنها تعرف أن الخيال
cannot be contained in buildings,
لا يمكن أن يسجن بين الجدران
and so much of the work they do
لذا معظم العروض التي تقدمها
is site-specific or outdoor work.
تكون في مواقع مفتوحة
So, the new festival, it asks the audience to play
المهرجانات الجديدة تطلب من الجمهور
an essential role in shaping the performance.
تأدية دور أساسي في العرض
Companies like De La Guarda, which I produce, and Punchdrunk
وشركات مثل "دي لا جاردا"، التي أنتج لها، و"بنش درنك"
create these completely immersive experiences
تقيم مهرجانات كهذه
that put the audience at the center of the action,
تصنع من الجمهور بطلا للعرض،
but the German performance company Rimini Protokoll
لكن شركة العروض الألمانية "ريميني بروتوكول"
takes this all to a whole new level.
تنتقل بالمهرجانات لمرحلة أخرى
In a series of shows that includes "100 Percent Vancouver,"
في سلسلة عروض، منها "100% فانكوفر"
"100 Percent Berlin," Rimini Protokoll makes shows
و "100% برلين"، تقيم "ريميني بروتوكول" عروضا
that actually reflect society.
تعكس روح المجتمع
Rimini Protokoll chooses 100 people that represent that city
فتختار مائة يمثلون المدينة في هذا الوقت
at that moment in terms of race and gender and class,
فيما يتعلق بالعِرق والجنس والطبقة
through a careful process that begins three months before,
من خلال عملية تستغرق ثلاثة أشهر
and then those 100 people share stories about
ثم يتشارك الـ 100 شخص قصصا
themselves and their lives, and the whole thing
حول أنفسهم وحول حياتهم
becomes a snapshot of that city at that moment.
ليتحول العرض إلى صورة للمدينة في هذه الفترة
LIFT has always been a pioneer in the use of venues.
لطالما كانت "ليفت" رائدة في اختيار المواقع
They understand that theater and performance
لأنها تعي أن العروض
can happen anywhere.
من الممكن أن تقام في أي مكان،
You can do a show in a schoolroom,
في فصل دراسي،
in an airport, — (Laughter) —
في مطار، (ضحك)
in a department store window.
في نافذة عرض لمتجر
Artists are explorers. Who better to show us the city anew?
الفنانون مستكشفونمن الأقدر على رؤية المدينة من زاوية أخرى؟
Artists can take us to a far-flung part of the city
قد يأخذنا الفنان إلى مكان في أطراف المدينة
that we haven't explored, or they can take us into
لم نستكشفه، أو يأخذنا إلى بنايات
that building that we pass every day but we never went into.
نمر بها يوميا ولم ندخلها قط
An artist, I think, can really show us people
أظن أن الفنان يمكنه تقديم أشخاص
that we might overlook in our lives.
لم ننتبه إليهم من قبل
Back to Back is an Australian company of people
"باك تو باك" شركة أسترالية
with intellectual disabilities. I saw their amazing show
تضم أشخاص معاقين ذهنيا،
in New York at the Staten Island Ferry Terminal
شاهدت عرضهم في محطة عبّارة جزيرة "ستاتن" بنيويورك
at rush hour.
في ساعة الذروة
We, the audience, were given headsets and seated
تم توزيع سماعات رأس علينا،
on one side of the terminal.
وجلسنا على أحد جوانب المحطة
The actors were right there in front of us,
كان الممثلون أمامنا
right there among the commuters,
وسط المسافرين
and we could hear them,
وكنا نسمعهم جيدا
but we might not have otherwise seen them.
لكننا لم نرهم طوال العرض
So Back to Back takes site-specific theater and uses it
"باك تو باك" تستخدم مواقع مميزة
to gently remind us about who and what we choose
لتذكرنا بما علينا أن نخرجه من حياتنا اليومية
to edit out of our daily lives.
وما علينا أن نحتفظ به
So, the dialogue with the local and the global,
الحوار المحلي والعالمي،
the audience as participant and player and protagonist,
والجمهور كمشارك وصاحب دور رئيسي،
the innovative use of site, all of these things
والاستخدام المبتكر للمواقع،
come to play in the amazing work
كل هذه الأشياء تجتمع في العمل الرائع
of the fantastic French company Royal de Luxe.
الذي تقدمه الشركة الفرنسية المتميزة "رويال دي لوكس"
Royal de Luxe's giant puppets come into a city
حيث جاءت عرائسها الضخمة إلى المدينة
and they live there for a few days.
وظلت بها لأيام قليلة
For "The Sultan's Elephant," Royal de Luxe
وفي عرض "فيل السلطان"، انتقلت "رويال دي لوكس"
came to central London and brought it to a standstill
إلى وسط لندن، وأوقفت حركتها
with their story of a giant little girl and her friend,
بقصة الفتاة الضخمة صغيرة السن وصديقها
a time-traveling elephant.
الفيل المسافر عبر الزمن
For a few days, they transformed a massive city
ولأيام قليلة حولوا مدينة ضخمة
into a community where endless possibility reigned.
إلى مجتمع يتمتع بعدد لا نهائي من الإمكانات
The Guardian wrote, "If art is about transformation,
كتبت الجارديان: "إذا كان الفن أساسه التحول
then there can be no more transformative experience.
فهذه التجربة فنية بجدارة
What 'The Sultan's Elephant' represents is no less
ما يقدمه لنا "فيل السلطان"
than an artistic occupation of the city
بمثابة احتلال فني للمدينة
and a reclamation of the streets for the people."
وعودة الشوارع لأهلها."
We can talk about the economic impacts of these festivals
لهذه المهرجانات تأثير اقتصادي على المدن
on their cities, but I'm much [more] interested in many more things,
لكني مهتم بالحديث عن أشياء أخرى
like how a festival helps a city to express itself,
كيف تدفع هذه المهرجانات المدن للتعبير عن هويتها
how it lets it come into its own.
وتأكيد استقلالها
Festivals promote diversity,
المهرجانات تعزز الاختلاف
they bring neighbors into dialogue,
وتخلق حوارا بين الجيران
they increase creativity,
وترفع مستوى الإبداع
they offer opportunities for civic pride,
وتعد سببا لتعزيز الانتماء
they improve our general psychological well-being.
كما تحسن من الحالة النفسية
In short, they make cities better places to live.
باختصار، تحسن تجربة السكن في المدينة
Case in point:
وإليكم مثالا:
When "The Sultan's Elephant" came to London
حين عرض "فيل السلطان" في لندن
just nine months after 7/7, a Londoner wrote,
بعد تسعة أشهر من 7/7، كتب أحد أهل المدينة
"For the first time since the London bombings,
"لأول مرة منذ بداية تفجيرات لندن،
my daughter called up with that sparkle back in her voice.
هاتفتني ابنتي بصوت استعاد حيويته،
She had gathered with others
اجتمعت مع آخرين
to watch 'The Sultan's Elephant,' and, you know,
لمشاهدة عرض "فيل السلطان"،
it just made all the difference."
وفي الحقيقة كان له تأثيرا كبيرا."
Lyn Gardner in The Guardian has written
وكتب (لاين جاردنر) في الجارديان:
that a great festival can show us a map of the world,
أن المهرجان الرائع يمكنه تقديم خريطة للعالم
a map of the city and a map of ourselves,
وللمدينة ولأنفسنا أيضا،
but there is no one fixed festival model.
لكن ليس هناك نموذج محدد للمهرجانات
I think what's so brilliant about the festivals,
أظن أن أروع ما في المهرجانات،
the new festivals, is that they are really fully capturing
الجديدة منها، أنها حقا تلتقط تعقيدات حياتنا
the complexity and the excitement
وتعكس الإثارة
of the way we all live today.
التي تميز أسلوب حياتنا الآن.
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا لكم. (تصفيق)